But now the subject that we really want
to talk about and that people don't know
much about. A lot of people are very
good at iron deficiency. They don't
understand iron overload as much.
Mhm. So now let's talk about iron
overload.
Iron, like I said before, is necessary
for life, but it's also a toxin.
And it's a toxin that is
bioaccumulative. It accumulates and we
don't have any physiological way of
getting rid of iron. Once iron is
absorbed, you cannot get rid of it.
So
there's a study that showed
the the relationship between
testosterone and ferritin. So it's an
interesting relationship. So when we
when we grow and then we go through our
growth period, this is when you know,
like puberty
and then you you you you grow. You get a
peak of testosterone during puberty,
right? 12, 13, 15, 20s. This is the time
where you get muscle growth, bone
growth, everything is growing.
This is the time that you are in an
anabolic period naturally. So your
testosterone level goes up and they've
seen that this is the time that you get
the most iron absorption also.
This is the time also that you have the
lowest iron stores as a man because your
body is utilizing iron to create new
muscle, new bone, new brain connection.
So just think about when you were 14,
15, 16. You would grow in a summer. I
grew 4 inches in a summer. I built
muscles. You need iron for this. You
need testosterone. So testosterone and
iron are very closely regulated
together. So the usual way is for a man
men and women, but men because they have
more testosterone, they grow more
muscles. When they go through puberty,
their testosterone levels go up, their
iron absorption goes up. You may see
that their ferritin and their iron
indices are lower because whatever you
absorb, your body uses it
to grow muscle, to grow a bone.
But starting at the age of about 30,
the iron it's we've grown already.
There's no more growing. So the iron
iron requirements decrease. They go back
to normal. Testosterone also from the
age of 30 kind of goes down. So iron and
testosterone work together. But the body
again is very smart. So when you get
that push of iron in your teens, iron
decreases hepsidin.
And it decreases hepsidin, so it leaves
open the channel to get more iron into
our blood from the gut and from the
spleen to put it in there. So remember
that that relationship, that
testosterone decreases hepsidin because
it has a lot to do with hemochromatosis.
Right? So now
what happens starting the age of 30,
everybody starts accumulating iron
because in our diet, we eat way too much
iron. In the US and many countries in in
in Europe, they added iron to our food,
to mostly every flour, every every
grain. So anything you're eating in the
US, if you're eating crackers, bread,
cereal,
pasta, anything with grain,
it has iron in it. And they put organic
iron that has a high absorption rate. So
they did this to help combat iron
deficiency in women. It still existed.
But now they exposed too much iron to a
lot of people who don't need iron. Men
after the age of 30, they don't need to
take more iron. They've already
accumulated the iron. Unless you're
bleeding, you're in an accident, your
body has more than enough iron stores to
keep the function of what is necessary.
Because it's only a very small amount of
iron that the body needs. Uh the RDA,
the recommended daily allowance of iron
is only 8 mg a day.
We use in our body maybe 1 to 2 mg to do
all of it and most of it comes from the
recycling from the spleen. So we don't
need that much iron from our diet and
that's why
um
1,000 years ago when you lived in in a
iron-poor environment,
having the gene that helps you conserve
iron was a benefit.
Evolutionary benefit.
Now we don't need that cuz iron is
everywhere.
So after the age of 30, most people
don't need extra iron.
So now as iron continues accumulating in
our body, it's bioaccumulative,
what happens is iron forms those
radicals and iron is also participates
in another the the creation of another
molecule called lipofuscin. Lipofuscin
is called the brown pigment. This is
junk. It's gunk. It's almost like if you
change your engine and you see the oil
that's all burnt out all around the
engine, that's almost what it looks
like. And this is what iron
can form as radicals and it goes all
into our cells, our mitochondria and it
creates junk.
It's rust. It's gunk. So this is what
iron does. So I'm looking at somebody
like you, even with a ferritin the 140,
you're creating excess oxidants, excess
oxidative stress. How do we help you
deal with this? So the way you deal with
this is first you want to minimize the
amount of oxidants who are coming in,
right? And with you
for some reason your body is processing
it very well. You're not high. You're
out of optimal range, but still what do
you do with this? You want to make sure
that you take the right antioxidants to
help you deal. That's what we do and why
we take antioxidants. We know it's to
improve cellular function. Well, iron
management is part of cellular function.
And when you take antioxidants, it also
helps you deal with the excess
generation of ROS from the extra iron.
And antioxidants are things like
glutathione, the number one very
important.
Quercetin, really important polyphenol.
Curcumin,
selenium, milk thistle, silymarin,
boron. A lot of those things, those um
um
Yeah, the glutathione peroxidase. You
take glutathione to make that. So all of
those antioxidants help balance out the
oxidants that you're creating too much
of. So yes, you want more antioxidants,
but how do you also decrease your
oxidant formation? Is by keeping your
ferritin and your iron within the
optimal func- functional medicine range,
which would be between 40 to 70.
This is where you're good. And the
problem is if you go too low, usually
below 30, you will be symptomatic. So it
is just like everything in medicine,
it's the balance.
[Music]